[WIGGINS] Okay, everyone.
Keep back, it's dangerous here.
Holmes had an
experiment backfire.
And the explosion seems
to have blown up the flat.
He says he'll offer all youse
a free consultation
to make up for it.
But right now,
he needs everyone to leave.
[WATSON]
The Lord of Crime?
So, Miss Adler was dealing
with him this entire time,
and not the government
like she claimed.
Are you absolutely
certain, Sherlock?
[HOLMES groans]
Listen! We know
the man's a killer!
I find it hard to believe
he'll keep any promise!
It's not like we can just let
Adler walk out the door!
No, it can't be that.
It seems there's no way
to save her at this point.
And, yet...
Damn it all!
[BOTH gasp]
Concentrate!
There must be something else!
So why can't I think of it?!
What're you talking about?
[HOLMES] It's hopeless.
No matter what, I always
arrive at the same conclusion.
All we can do is go with
the worst-case scenario.
[footsteps]
[HUDSON, WATSON grunt]
[HUDSON]
Miss Adler.
I haven't visited for very long,
but thank you for
your hospitality.
I was looking forward to having
a long conversation
over some tea.
[ADLER] Thank you,
Miss Hudson, as was I.
[HOLMES] This really
is goodbye, isn't it?
Oh, Sherly, don't tell
me you're going to miss me
that much after
I'm out of your hair.
I'm sure you'll recover.
[chuckles] The "tough girl" act.
[ADLER chuckles]
[HOLMES]
Irene.
This deal that's arranged--
are you certain it's going to
save you in the end?
Without a doubt.
I may have messed
things up a bit,
but I finally found a way out
and can see the light
at the end of the tunnel.
[HOLMES] She's bluffing,
and fully expects to be killed.
Well, good. That's a relief.
[HOLMES]
It was her fault for stealing
something so pernicious.
Still though,
when it comes to her desire to
make the world a better place,
there's nothing false behind it.
It's up to me.
I have to keep her safe.
[ALBERT] You really
believe this plan of yours
will entice Sherlock
Holmes to show up?
[WILLIAM]
Of course.
I guarantee he'll
make an appearance.
All for Irene Adler's sake.
He has no interest in
the document itself.
His first thought will likely be
to safeguard Miss Adler from
any harm that would befall her.
Which means he'll
be too distracted
to uncover our identities.
But the downside is
unless Holmes receives
assurance Adler's life
is no longer in
any sort of danger,
there's no chance of him
backing down, is there?
Once again, we'll be
relying on you, Will.
[WILLIAM]
Yes.
I have a plan to
put his mind at ease.
[OLD WOMAN]
Am I safe in presuming
you're Miss Irene Adler?
The gentleman you're to meet
has already arrived
and is waiting for you.
This way.
[ALBERT]
Welcome, Irene Adler.
[ADLER grunts]
[ADLER]
I've brought the document,
but please, allow me
to verify one thing.
[ADLER] These reforms you
say will better the world.
You swear you're
telling me the truth?
[ALBERT] Of course,
our objectives are the same.
However, if you
feel they don't align,
you're free to
accuse me of such.
I shall take your word.
[ALBERT] All right then,
as a token of your loyalty,
hand me the document.
[HOLMES] Sorry, but you
can't turn it over yet.
[gasps]
Sherlock, wait!
Well, Sherlock Holmes.
So, you did show up after all.
You're the Lord of Crime?
We meet at last.
[ADLER] Answer me.
What are you doing here?
[HOLMES]
Keeping you safe, what else?
[ADLER]
Seriously?
[HOLMES] But don't worry.
I didn't come alone!
- -[inhales]
- -[whistle sounds]
Scotland Yard?!
[HOLMES]
There's nowhere for you to run.
It's over.
You're going to get
yourself killed, too!
Take it easy, Irene, and
let me handle this, all right?
But, Sherlock...
[ALBERT chuckles] Are you
planning on arresting me?
[HOLMES] That all
depends entirely on you.
Go on then.
[HOLMES] After learning the
contents of these papers,
my first thought was naturally
how I could protect
Irene from the fallout.
As long as the possibility
exists she'll leak them,
then regardless of what
happens to the documents,
the government will still
try to eliminate her.
Which presents one solution:
Find some way to get
her out of the country.
But the certitude of
that plan is in doubt.
So, what can I do to
completely ensure her safety?
The answer is to have her
protected by someone else.
An individual operating in
the underworld of London
who has complete autonomy.
In other words, someone
like you, Lord of Crime.
I hate to admit it,
but you're the only one
capable of protecting her.
Obviously, as I've
already informed her,
part of our arrangement
is I keep her alive.
No one else can offer
her the same guarantee.
But I am sure it will take more
than my word to convince you.
[BOTH grunt]
[ALBERT] Irene Adler. Write
my name on this piece of paper,
seal it in the envelope,
and hand it to him.
Holmes, if there comes
a time when you determine
she has been dispatched, you're
free to open the envelope,
read my name,
and then come for me.
Agree to place your trust
in me, Sherlock Holmes,
and I will do the same for you.
Fine by me.
[pen scratching]
[ADLER]
It's done.
And I have it
in my possession.
Then with that,
our business is concluded.
You may leave, along with your
so-called police force.
[ADLER gasps]
[HOLMES]
So, you knew all along?
[ALBERT] Forgive me,
but I must take my leave.
Farewell, Sherlock Holmes.
[footsteps]
[HOLMES] Generous of him to
allow us to say our goodbyes.
[ADLER]
You've done so much for me.
There's no possible way I could
ever express my gratitude.
I'll pass your
thanks on to John.
[ADLER] Until now, I've done
nothing but lie to you.
So, I doubt you'll take my word
for this, but...
...the truth is
I am rather fond of you.
[HOLMES chuckles]
Still lying.
I swear to you, I'm not!
[ADLER chuckles]
[ADLER] Promise me one thing.
You won't forget about me?
I couldn't forget
even if I wanted to.
[ADLER]
Farewell, my detective.
[HOLMES] As long as you're
alive, I know we'll meet again.
[footsteps]
There's a passageway
like this beneath the church?
[gasps]
Holmes made an appearance,
like you said.
And the transaction
concluded smoothly.
Your cunning plan
saved us, Will, again.
[WILLIAM]
Excellent to hear, Brother.
[ADLER]
By the sound of it,
they were anticipating
Sherlock's interference.
Is it possible?
No, there's no doubt about it.
When it comes to
the Lord of Crime,
the title doesn't refer
to a single one person.
As for the heart of
the organization...
My life is in your hands,
I pledge my service.
And in exchange
for your loyalty,
I shall bestow upon you
what you desire most.
Come, Irene Adler.
[grunts]
I believe you and I should
make our way to
the final negotiation.
It seems I was mistaken.
And here I thought you
were smarter than this.
You managed to
recover the document,
as well as liquidate Adler.
At least, that's what was
written in your telegram.
I trust there's an explanation.
[ALBERT] The contents
proved extremely fascinating.
Who could have ever
guessed the French Revolution
was a social
experiment set up by us?
In addition, that
Maximilien Robespierre,
the mastermind behind the plot,
and author of the document,
was an agent working
for Britain all along.
Indeed, these pages
detail the exact effort
used by the British Empire
to instigate the upheaval
of French society.
Imagine if these papers
were ever made public.
Our allied nations would
be completely justified
in going to war
against us in retaliation
for meddling in another
country's affairs.
I grow increasingly
weary of these games.
My sole interest is ascertaining
whether you're an
enemy of Britain.
[ALBERT] And I have but
a single request of you:
your absolute silence.
[MYCROFT grunts]
[ALBERT]
Ever since I was young,
I have sought to
expose corruption.
To bring to light the
misdeeds of the nobility
in an effort to collapse
the class system.
[MYCROFT]
I see.
So, you're the one
everybody's talking about,
the "Lord of Crime."
[WILLIAM] Guilty. Everything
that has transpired
has been engineered
to further our goal.
Collectively, we are
"James Moriarty."
Unmasking yourself now?
My investigation revealed you
had effective collaborators.
If I'm not mistaken, you are...
Call me William,
Director Holmes.
The Lord of Crime accompanied
by both his left and right hand.
As for our ultimate objective--
it's the same as the
author of these papers:
rid the world of tyrants and
bring equality to our homeland.
The leader of
the French Revolution
was Maximilien Robespierre.
Following the execution of
King Louis the 16th,
he abruptly preached for the
necessity of the Reign of Terror
and carried out the purge.
[WILLIAM]
History has painted him
as one of the great villains
behind the Revolution.
His actions were
difficult to comprehend
through conventional thinking.
However, there was
a reason behind the madness.
His goal was to
overthrow the monarchy
and place control of the country
in the hands of its people.
[WILLIAM]
He managed to execute the king
and the revolution
appeared to be a success.
However...
...as a direct result of
vilifying the ruling class,
the people clamoured for
the nobility to be killed.
The situation quickly
spiralled out of his control.
In response, he decided
to adopt a new measure...
...what became known
as the Reign of Terror.
[WILLIAM]
Aristocrats and citizens
who opposed the
revolution were executed,
one after another.
[WILLIAM]
The indiscriminate bloodshed
turned the people's ire
from the nobility
onto Robespierre.
[WILLIAM] He created a common
enemy for both sides to loath.
[CROWD shouting]
[WOMAN 14A]
Death to all tyrants!
[WILLIAM] The Terror was put
to rest with one last death:
his own.
And now, we're
attempting to achieve
the same results for
Britain in these modern times.
[WILLIAM] Our aim is to
redistribute power,
dividing it as
equally as possible.
By employing crime to that end,
we will become
the common "evil."
Despised by both the
nobility and the people,
allowing both sides
to unite hand-in-hand.
Eventually, we will
meet the same fate
that befell Robespierre.
When the full weight of
our sins comes to light,
the Moriartys will have to die.
[ALBERT] Now that you know
our plans, what will yours be?
If you wish to
sacrifice yourselves
in an act of patriotism,
go ahead.
I've no intention
of interfering.
That is, however,
assuming the three of you
really are patriots.
If I decide at any time
you are out of control,
then as enemies of Britain,
you will be eliminated.
That is a promise.
As would be your right.
There is a reason why we
revealed ourselves to you.
There are those who say you are
the government itself.
Very well, then.
Speaking on behalf of
the British government,
you have my solemn word.
We'll remain silent
towards your activity.
You have our
gratitude, Director.
This is yours, sir, but
permit me to ask one question.
Why keep this document
instead of destroying it?
You continue to run the risk
of it being stolen again.
Surely there has to be a reason.
Two reasons actually.
First, her Majesty feels that
the failure of this mission
is a crime for which Britain
must shoulder
the weight indefinitely.
The other reason
is more personal.
See, Maximilien Robespierre,
the author responsible for
penning this document--
his true name was
Sherrinford Holmes.
[gasps]
[MYCROFT]
An ancestor of mine.
This is our family's punishment,
one we must continue to bear.
And the reason why I continue
to pledge loyalty to
the British Government.
[MYCROFT chuckles]
My dear brother's not
aware of any of this.
You can understand.
I prefer him to live
free of the knowledge.
Now then, enough
of this idle talk.
[gasps]
[MYCROFT]
Our deal has been struck.
[PEOPLE chattering]
[MYCROFT] I trust I find you
in good health, Doctor Watson.
[WATSON]
Mycroft, hello.
Did you need to
speak with Sherlock?
I'm afraid it appears he's
stepped out for the moment.
Yes, perhaps it is
better this way.
[WATSON]
Hm?
There is a woman for whom
my brother has given his all.
He may even have had
special feelings for her.
That is why I wanted to come
and tell him
about this directly.
Good night and goodbye,
Mister Sherlock Holmes.
[HOLMES grunts]
[HUDSON, WATSON grunt]
Sherlock, I...
[HUDSON sobs]
What's the matter with you two?
You look as if you've
seen a ghost or something.
[BOTH grunt]
[WATSON]
Actually, you see...
...Mycroft came by
with a message for you.
Word is... Miss Adler
has passed away.
And that her body was
pulled out of the Thames.
[ALBERT]
If there comes a time when you
determine she has
been dispatched,
you're free to
open the envelope,
read my name,
and then come for me.
[chuckles]
[HOLMES]
She's dead. "The woman" is dead.
That's the truth, isn't it?
[ALBERT] It's time to
carry out our final job.
[ALBERT] Go, Fred, and
select a body from the morgue
that'll prove to be a
suitable stand-in for her.
[FRED]
It shall be done.
Irene, as of this moment,
you are no longer
among the living.
You are a member
of this organization
and we're going
to put you to work.
Right.
It goes without saying
you'll need a new identity.
For your first name,
we'll give you ours.
Thus, you'll be known as James.
As for your last name...
This marks the
start of a new life.
New friends. New bonds...
My name should reflect that.
The name is James Bonde.
[BONDE] Next time on
Moriarty the Patriot  :
"The Phantom of
Whitechapel Act One."